Quite an Arctic storm blowing out there
Hm! Come along, Polly, my child, with my cloak
Doctor, you've got the most fantastic wardrobe.Yes
We don't know what we're in for outside there
Pretty soon we shall be having visitors
You're different. You've got no feelings
I do not understand that word
Emotions. Love, pride, hate, fear
Have you no emotions, sir?
What's happened to you, Doctor?
I guess this old body of mine is wearing a bit thin
Doctor! Wakey, wakey, it's all over now
No
It isn't all over
It's far from being all over
What are you talking about?
I must get back to the TARDIS
I can't go through with it. I will fight it
I will not change
Hello? Is someone there?
Hello?
Who is that?
I'm the Doctor
Oh, I don't think so. No, dear me, no
You may be A Doctor, but I am THE Doctor
The original, you might say
You!
How can it...be you?
Do I know you, sir?
This is the South Pole! We're at the South Pole!
Of course we are. Don't you know that?
This is where it happened
Where what happened?
This is it...
The very first time that I... well, you, WE regenerated
You're mid-regeneration, aren't you?
Your face, it's all over the place - but you're trying to hold it back
What do you know of regeneration? Are you a Time Lord?
You know who I am. You must.Hm!
Have you come to take the ship back?
The ship? You still call it a ship!
Oh, dear, what have you done to it?
Nothing.The windows...
I don't remember this. ..they're the wrong size!
The colour...I don't remember trying not to change
..I'm sure it's changed! Not back then
Look at it. It seems to have...expanded!
Well, it's all those years of bigger on the inside -
You try sucking your tummy in that long
Why are you trying not to regenerate?
I have the courage and the right to live and die as myself
Too late, it's started
A few minutes ago, you were weak as a kitten, right?
Now you're fine. We're in a state of grace, both of us...
..but it won't last long. We have a choice
Either we change and go on - or we die as we are...
..but if you, if you die here...
..if your future never happens
If you don't do the things that you are supposed to do
The consequences could be...
The snow?The snow?
Look at it!
How extraordinary
Everything's stopped
But why?
Maybe it's us. Maybe it's something else...
..but somehow, something has gone very wrong with time
Hello?
Sorry
So sorry
I don't suppose either of you is a doctor?
You trying to be funny?
EXPLOSIONS
There is something I should like to say
That is, there is something I should very much like you to understand
I do not have the slightest desire to kill you
The only reason I would do so is self-defence
However, since you are aware I might kill you in self-defence
There is the strong possibility you will kill me in self-defence
Does rather make me wish you understood English
Lass mich einfach hier
Ich will dich nicht toten, bitte geh
Or that I spoke German
War is hell, eh?
SWOOSHING
FEMALE VOICE:Timeline error. There is a timeline error
Timeline error. There is a timeline error
Everything's stopped
But why?
Maybe it's us. Maybe it's something else...
..but somehow, something has gone very wrong with time
Hello?
Sorry. So sorry
I don't suppose either of you is a doctor?
Are you trying to be funny?
She's coming! She's coming!
It's her
Not human, I think
State your planet of origin and your intentions
This is Earth. A level five civilisation
And it is protected.It's what?
Oh. OK. That doesn't usually work
Protected by whom?
Oh, it is early days, isn't it?
May I suggest, for your own safety, you step on board my ship?
What ship?
He means, get inside the box
A little snug from this angle, but you might be in for a sur...
My TARDIS! Look at my TARDIS!
This is impossible!
Have I been burgled?
It's...but it's...
Hideous!
..bigger on the inside than it is on the outside!
You know, I thought it probably was -
I'm glad it's not just me
What is this place?
This place is, or ought to be, my TARDIS
Technically, that is your TARDIS
It's about 70 feet that way, see?
Always remember where you parked, it's going to come up a lot
Is this madness? Am I going mad?
Madness?
Well, you're an officer from World War I, at the South Pole
Being pursued by an alien through frozen time
Madness was never this good
World War I?
Judging by the uniform, yes
Yes, but what do you mean...one?
Oh, sorry. Spoilers
Enough of this! Who are you?Um...
You know who I am. You knew the moment you saw me
I'd say stop being an idiot, but I kind of know what's coming
I assure you I do not have the faintest idea who you are!
Well, I know who you are
Is anyone going to explain what's going on?
Snap
You are me?
No! No!
Yes, yes, I'm very much afraid so
Do I become you?
Well, there's a few false starts, but you get there in the end
But I thought...
What? Well. I assumed, I'd get...younger
I am younger!
You know, I really don't think I'm completely following
Oh...
Oh, dear
Oh, you're in shock - let me help you
Brandy, get him brandy, do you have any?
I had some somewhere
Hang on!
Sit down here, my boy, collect your wits
Who are you people?
I am the Doctor, and this is my, um...
It's complicated, actually - I am also...
..my nurse
Excuse me?
I realise that seems a little improbable...
Well, yes... ..because he's a man
What?!Older gentlemen, like women, can be put to use
You can't... You can't say things like that
Can't I? Says who?
Just about everyone you're going to meet for the rest of your life
Here
Have you had some of this?
Well, you know, I may have snuck a glass
At some point in the last 1,500 years -
It's been rock and roll
There you are, get this down you. You'll feel a lot better
Thank you, yes
I... I don't understand any of this
Of course you understand. I am your future self
Are you, indeed?
And I suppose this is meant to be my TARDIS?
Our TARDIS
What's wrong with the lights?
It's supposed to be like this
Why?It's atmospheric
Atmospheric?
This is the flight deck of the most powerful space-time machine
In the known universe, not a restaurant for the French
Good Lord, what is that?
Oh, look what someone has accidentally left here
I say, it's some sort of guitar, isn't it?
Oh, is it yours?
It appears to have been played quite recently
It's the only thing here that's been cleaned
In fact, this whole place could do with a good dusting
Obviously Polly isn't around any more
Please, please, please stop saying things like that
RUMBLING AND CLATTERING
Can't get the engines to start
There's some kind of signal blocking the command path
FEMALE VOICE:Exit your capsule, the Chamber of the Dead awaits you
I'll fix the engines, while you keep her talking
Fields up
Look around you
You stand in the Chamber of the Dead
You are known to all here, for you are the Doctor of War
The Doctor, yes - but the Doctor of War?
Never, ma'am, never
We offer you a gift
Return to us the human on your TARDIS
And in exchange, you may speak with her again
Speak with whom?
Young lady, who are you?
Is he here? Is the Doctor here?
Doctor!
I knew it!
I did, I knew it
I knew you couldn't be dead, you don't have the concentration
Doctor?
What are you doing?
Just keep still, please
Bill Potts.Yeah
My friend Bill Potts was turned into a Cyberman
She gave her life so that people she barely knew could live
So, let's be clear
Nobody imitates Bill Potts
Nobody mocks Bill Potts
Bill Potts is standing right in front of you
How is that even possible?
Long story short - I totally pulled
You... You did what?
Heather - do you remember, the girl in the puddle?
She showed up, she came for me
How romantic. Where is she?
Well, she's...
She's...
And how did you get here?
I... I... I can't...
You can't remember. No, I bet you can't
SONIC SCREWDRIVER WHIRS
That device, what is it?
A sonic screwdriver
A... A what screwdriver?
It's really a very good job
An audio screwdriver?
There are only three low-key markers indicating that she's a duplicate
I'm not a duplicate!
So, who has been stealing the faces of the dead?
Time travel technology, obviously
From the far future
I know
Sunglasses?
They're sonic!
Indoors?
So, What are you?
We are what awaits at the end of every life
As every living soul dies, so we will appear
We take from you what we need
And return you to the moment of your death
We are...Testimony
You come from the distant future?
You travel back in time
Find people on the exact point of death, and what?
You harvest something from them?
Yes
On behalf of the dying
What is it that we have that the future needs so badly?
And what has any of this to do with a War World I captain
Landing at the South Pole, in the wrong decade?
We were returning him to the appointed time
And place of his death
An error in the timeline ejected him into the wrong time zone
Now his death must proceed as history demands
If I may
Who were you?
She wasn't anyone
SONIC SCREWDRIVER WHIRS
She's a computer-generated interface
Connected to a multiform, inter-phasing data-bank...
Oh, for heaven's sake
Will you put that ridiculous buzzing toy away, and look at the woman!
You see?
Her face, it's very slightly asymmetrical
If it were computer-generated, it wouldn't produce that effect
Yes. You're absolutely right. I should have noticed that
Well, it might help if you could see properly!
Er...excuse me... Doctor!
Get back inside!
I'm not quite sure, but it seemed to me
That this young lady's life was being offered
In exchange for my own
As it happens, I think my number is pretty much up anyway
What are you talking about? Doctor, what's he talking about?
So, might as well make it count for something, eh?
I should be happy to take your place
If that would resolve this situation
GLASS WOMAN:Accepted
That is not happening. That's totally not happening
Agreed?
Tell me what to do, then
Bill Potts would tell me what to do
Do what you always do
Serve at the pleasure of the human race
Here's what's going to happen
First, I'm going to escape!
You, with me!
Where are we going?
Escape is not possible
It is possible, and it is happening
And I'm taking Bill and the Captain with me
Why are you advertising your intentions?
Can't you stop boasting for a moment?
Mr Pastry, too, I could do with a laugh
Escape is not possible
Oh, I'm going to do way more than escape
I'm going to find out who you are and what you're doing
And if I don't like it, I will come back
And I will stop you. I will stop all of you!
Who the hell do you think you are?
The Doctor
I am the Doctor
Who you are, I cannot begin to imagine
Then let us show you, Doctor. See who you will become
Doctor!Exterminate!
You will be assimilated
No. No, that's not a good idea!
They all died
The Doctor has walked in blood through all of time and space
The Doctor has many names
..the destroyer of the world...
The Imp of the Pandorica
The Shadow of the Valeyard
The Beast of Trenzalore
The Butcher of Skull Moon
The Last Tree of Garsennon
The Destroyer of Skaro
He is the Doctor of War
What... What was that?
To be fair, they cut out all the jokes
Do what I do when I do it
SONIC SCREWDRIVER WHIRS
Jump!
They are not escaping
What do we do now?
Run!
Where? They've got the TARDIS
Yes, that's exactly what they're supposed to think
But they do, though, look!
They've got my TARDIS - over to you, Mary Berry
Come on
Doctor, is that...another TARDIS?
No, no. It's another of the same TARDIS
Hang on, the windows are the wrong size!
Inside, quickly!
Take off, now! Deep space, anywhere! VWORP
I tell you what, these police boxes -
They're ever so good, aren't they?
The navigation systems don't function properly
I'm unable to program our flight with any accuracy
So, my dear, I presume you travel with him
Used to. Kind of miss it
Well, he clearly misses you
That ship of his is in dire need of a good spring clean
No, no, no, stop, stop, stop talking
Look, look, look, look at the astral map!
Look at all the lovely blinking lights, look at that
He's you!
He is, isn't he? He's you
He's one of your old faces
I'm find I'm lagging behind a tiny bit again. You...
Not those again, I forbid it!
There you go, I was right. Asymmetrical
I said that
Same difference
If her face was based on a human original
Perhaps identifying who that was
Will tell us what we need to know about Testimony
Why am I wearing these?
Because I love it. Never take those off
What's "browser history"?
I'm trying to match her face in the TARDIS data bank
But there's hardly anything in it yet. We need a bigger database
Possibly the Matrix on Gallifrey
No. We need something bigger than the Matrix
So basically, we're trying to track the glass lady, yes?
Basically
A striking looking creature
Quite beautiful, really, isn't she?
Yeah, if you like ladies made of glass
Well, aren't all ladies made of glass, in a way?
Very good, sir, very good
Are we now?
Oh, my dear
I hope it doesn't offend you to know
That I have some experience of the fairer sex
Me too
Good Lord
VWORP STOPS
Where are we?
But you steered the ship, you piloted her perfectly
We are at the very centre of the universe
Out there is the most comprehensive database of all life anywhere
There is just one little problem
Which is?
It wants to kill me
CHITTERING
The Weapon Forges of Villengard
Once the nightmare of the seven galaxies
Now home to the dispossessed
I say, I think there's something moving over here
Step away, please
Probably just rats - I'm used to rats
Deep breaths, deep breaths. Just breathe, Captain, you'll be fine
That creature - it looked familiar
It's mutated a bit, but, yes, I should think it did
Come along, my dear chap, you'll be fine
Get him into the TARDIS
What are those things?
What we came here for
The biggest database in the galaxy
They'll settle down in a moment
So, do we talk to them?
Ask them questions, how does it work?
"We" don't do anything. I do.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no!
You're going to wait in the TARDIS. Why?
Because you need to look after the captain
You're lying. You think I'm a duplicate, a trick
I don't know what I think
But if there is the slightest chance that Bill Potts is alive
And standing in front of me
Then I will not, under any circumstances
Put her life in danger again
Seriously?
You're looking right at me and you don't even know I'm here
Correct
I ask you to respect that, and respect me...
You're an arse. Do you know that?
You're a... You're a stupid bloody arse
..as I have always respected you
If I hear any more language like that from you, young lady
You're in for a jolly good smacked bottom
Can we just pretend that that never happened?
I'm a broad-minded girl -
I mean, I know we have this whole professor/student thing going on...
Can we never, ever talk about this again?
I hope we talk about it loads
I hope we spend years laughing about it
Come back alive
Be here when I do
Perhaps another nip of brandy?
So that's where it went
I'll look after him
Good girl, quite right
Now, young lady, I don't want to have to repeat myself
I don't think any of us want that
I'll see you both presently
Brandy?
Please
CHITTERING
These creatures - what are they?
Old friends of ours - but they've really come out of their shell
Out of their shell...
Are you all right?
I'll be fine in a moment
What's the matter?
I died a few hours ago - then I refused to regenerate
It catches up with you, you know, it's like a big lunch
I did exactly the same
I know you did - but why?
I don't remember this, why are you refusing the regeneration?
Fear
I'm afraid. Very, very afraid
I don't normally admit that to anyone else
Don't worry - technically, you still haven't
Why are you?
There's something in that tower!
Must be my friend
Why are you calling him your friend?
He's got a great big gun, are you suggesting I insult him?
Scan me, go on. Scan me
Because I've got big news for you
I'm dying
You see, it's true
Dying
Now. Be honest with yourself
Wouldn't you like to see that up close?
RATTLING
Come on, up and at 'em, Corporal Jones
Funny thing. I wasn't afraid in the crater
One doesn't want to die, of course
But one gets in a certain frame of mind
One pulls oneself together, and gets on with the matter in hand
Big shock for everyone back in Cromer, of course
You have family?
My wife will miss me, that's perfectly natural...
..but she's a solid woman. Remarkably solid
And my boys...
Well, sons are supposed to move on from their fathers
It's the proper way
Of course
Trouble is, I thought I'd been rescued
Felt rather like a miracle, in fact...
..but I do have this feeling they're going to put me back
Back in that crater in time to die...
..and, you see, I'm not ready any more
I've lost the idea of it. That's the trouble with hope
Makes one awfully frightened
HE CHUCKLES
I must sound like the most dreadful coward
OK. I'd better go up alone
I won't hear of it
That thing up there won't miss the chance to kill me twice
The paradox would rip the universe apart -
And you know how much hard work it is putting it back together again
You keep a lookout down here
Oh, if you insist
BEEPING
You know what? You're a bit of a legend these days...
..but not everyone believes it
People don't think that it could happen
That someone like you could turn against your own kind
Because your kind don't do that
Out of their shells!
Because people don't believe there could be any such thing...
..as a good Dalek
I am not a good Dalek. You are a good Dalek
Oh! Hello, my dear
Now, Rusty, you know that I'm dying...
..and if you don't want me to go off and die somewhere else
Where you can't watch, you're going to have to stop shooting at me
I agree to your terms
Well, I'm going to need some proof
WHIRRING
ELECTRICAL SPARKING
You know what?
You are the very first Dalek that ever got naked for me
You're the first one, yeah? Like, the original version of the Doctor
My dear, you should get back to the ship, this place isn't safe
You're the one who stole the TARDIS and ran away
The Captain might be needing you
The Captain's fine. Why did you do it?
Oh, I'm sure your Doctor has explained
I'm not even sure he remembers
There were many pressing reasons
I don't mean what you ran away from -
What were you running to?
That's rather a good question
Questions are kind of my thing
How are you with answers?
It's been a long time - remember the good old days?
When I got miniaturised and I climbed around inside you?
You taught me to hate the Daleks
Billions of years ago. What have you been up to since then?
Destroying Daleks
Yes, all the ones who come here to murder you
Yes, I saw the mess outside
Why are you here?
As a Dalek, you are linked in to the Dalek hive mind
All Daleks are - biggest database I know
I'd like to access it
Why would I help you?
Because...helping me, in any way...
..does something wonderful
It hurts the Daleks
There is good and there is evil
I left Gallifrey to answer a question of my own
By any analysis, evil should always win
Good is not a practical survival strategy -
It requires loyalty, self-sacrifice and love
So, why does good prevail?
What keeps the balance between good and evil in this appalling universe?
Is there some kind of logic? Some mysterious force?
Perhaps there's just a bloke
A "bloke"?
Yeah
Perhaps there's just some bloke, wandering around
Putting everything right when it goes wrong?
Well, that would be a nice story, wouldn't it?
That would be the best
But the real world is not a fairy tale
You dash around the universe
Trying to figure out what's holding it all together
And you really, really don't know?
You know me in the future, do I ever understand?
No...
I really don't think you do
Everyone who's ever met you does
You're amazing, Doctor
Never forget that
Never, ever
Well...that's very kind of you
We just needed to understand you, Doctor
Professor Helen Clay, University Of New Earth
Year five billion and twelve
There's footage - can you run it?
A spy
A spy in the camp!
No, not a spy
I'm Bill Potts...
..but I'm part of Testimony now
The Testimony Foundation combines the resources of time travel
With the latest in memory extraction techniques
The near-dead can be lifted momentarily from their time streams
Their memories duplicated
And then their physical selves returned
To the moment of their dissolution, without pain
Distress or any recall of the process
Now the dead can speak again
We can hear the testimony of the past
And, channelled through our glass avatars
They can walk among us again
This is Heaven on New Earth
Oh, it's not an evil plan
I don't really know what to do when it isn't an evil plan
Why did you stop it?
Rusty?
He didn't stop it. They've frozen time again
Who has?
Not everything's evil, Doctor
You're not the only kind one in the universe
I knew you weren't real!
Oh, shut up and stop being so stupid - of course I'm real
What is anyone supposed to be, except a bunch of memories?
These are my memories, so this is me
I'm Bill Potts, and I'm back, and so long as I'm here...
..what the hell do you mean, you're not going to regenerate?
There has to be an end, Bill - for everyone, everywhere
What about the Captain?
You know he has to die at his allotted point in time and space
To correct the error
I'm so tired of losing people
If the Captain has to die, a request
This was our fault
How so?
Let us take him back
How was this our fault?
You and me tried to die twice in the same lifetime
Our lives are woven throughout time and space
We caused the timeline error that put the Captain in the wrong place
We created a whirlpool in time that landed him at our feet
But why him? What's so important about one captain?
Everybody's important to somebody, somewhere
Are you all right?
Yes, fine, absolutely. Just thinking
I told the wife I'd be home for Christmas
Funny how things work out
VWORP
Thank you
Thank you all
You've all been most gracious in the unfortunate circumstances
I regret, Captain, that the universe generally fails to be a fairy tale
When time resumes, you will not remember this
A perception filter will also render us invisible
Yes
One imagines some of those words
Were attached to actual meanings of some sort
One thing you could possibly do for me, if you were very kind?
Oh, anything. Name it
My family
Perhaps you could look in on them, from time to time?
We should be delighted. What's the name?
Lethbridge-Stewart. Captain Archibald Hamish Lethbridge-Stewart
I shall make it my business
You can trust him on that
Thank you so much. I believe I am now ready
Das ist verruckt. Ich will dir nicht wehtun
Cold, isn't it?
It's about to get colder, I suppose - for one of us
SOLDIERS SING: # Stille Nacht, heilige Nacht
# Alles schlaft, einsam wacht... #
I say, is that singing?
# ..hochheilige Paar
# Holder Knabe im lockigen Haar
# Schlaf in himmlischer Ruh!
# Schlaf in himmlischer... #
Is that...Christmas carols?
# Silent night, holy night
# All is calm, all is bright... #
ENGLISH AND GERMAN SINGING MERGES
You know, I could swear it's coming from both sides
If I've got my timings right -
And clearly I have - then we should be right at the beginning
I adjusted the time frame, only by a couple of hours
Any other day it wouldn't make any difference
But this is Christmas 1914
And a human miracle is about to happen
The Christmas Armistice
Wounded man here! HE BLOWS HIS WHISTLE
Wounded man here, wounded man!
It never happened again. Any war, anywhere...
I say, wounded man here, wounded man!
..but for one day, one Christmas, a very long time ago...
..everyone just put down their weapons, and started to sing
Everybody just stopped
Everyone was just kind
You've saved him!
Both of them
Never hurts - a couple fewer dead people on the battlefield
So that's what it means to be a doctor of war
You were right, you know
The universe generally fails to be a fairy tale...
..but that's where we come in!
# For auld lang syne, my dear
# For auld lang syne
# We'll take a cup of kindness yet
# For auld lang syne, my dear
# For auld lang syne
# We'll take a cup of kindness yet
# For auld lang syne... #
I think I'm ready now...
..but I should like to know - are you?
You'll find out
The long way round
Whatever you decide - good luck, Doctor
Goodbye, Doctor
VWORP
Well, then. Here we go!
The long way round!
You OK?
Shall we go for one last stroll, Miss Potts?
Do you know what the hardest thing about knowing you was?
My superior intelligence. My dazzling charisma
Oh! My impeccable dress sense
Letting you go
Letting go of the Doctor is so, so hard
Isn't it?
You see, that's not the sort of thing the real Bill Potts would say
I am the real Bill!
A life is just memories - I'm all her memories, so I'm her
If you say so
OK. I'm going to prove to you how important memories are
I've got a little goodbye present for you
Oh, that's nice. Will I have to pretend I like it?
Because honestly, that rug...
Oh, come here, you
Merry Christmas, Doctor
Clara!
Hello, you stupid old man
You're back! You're in my head
All my memories...are back
And don't go forgetting me again, because...
..quite frankly, that was offensive
Memories - important, right?
I know what you're thinking - where is he?
Hello, sir!
When you're already dying
You're entitled to think that your day couldn't get any worse -
But here you are. And both of you are here
How does that work?
We can be everyone. We are everyone
Yeah, it's good this, innit?
Now I'm all made of glass, not just my nipples
Yeah - but they got my hair a bit wrong, though, didn't they?
You don't have any hair!
I have invisible hair
Got a suggestion for you, then
Oh, there's a novelty
Don't die
Because if you do, I think everybody in the universe might just go cold
Can't I ever have peace? Can't I rest?
Of course you can
It's your choice
Only yours
We understand
No. No, you don't. You're not even really here
You're just memories held in glass
Do you know how many of you I could fill?
I would shatter you
My testimony would shatter all of you
A life this long - do you understand what it is?
It's a battlefield, like this one...
..and it's empty
Because everyone else has fallen
Thank you
Thank you, both, for everything that you were to me
What happens now...
...where I go now...
..it has be alone
Cuddle
Time to leave the battlefield
VWORP
Oh, there it is
The silly old universe
The more I save it, the more it needs saving
It's a treadmill
Yes, yes, I know. They'll get it all wrong without me
I suppose one more lifetime wouldn't kill anyone
Well, except me
You wait a moment, Doctor
Let's get it right
I've got a few things to say to you
Basic stuff first
Never be cruel, never be cowardly...
..and never, ever eat pears!
Remember...
..hate is always foolish...
..and love is always wise
Always try to be nice, but never fail to be kind
Oh, and you mustn't tell anyone your name
No-one would understand it, anyway
Except...
Except children
Children can hear it...
..sometimes...
If their hearts are in the right place
And the stars are, too
Children can hear your name
Agh!
But nobody else
Nobody else, ever
Laugh hard...
..run fast...
..be kind
Doctor...
..I let you go
VWORP
Oh, brilliant!
SHE SCREAMS